<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Prachodayat&#x27;s sparks on Education - pedagogy</title>
	<subtitle>Prachodayat&#x27;s sparks on Education</subtitle>
	<link href="https://prachodayat.netlify.app/tags/pedagogy/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://prachodayat.netlify.app/"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://prachodayat.netlify.app/tags/pedagogy/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Story telling for all subjects</title>
		<published>2022-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://prachodayat.netlify.app/006-story-telling/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://prachodayat.netlify.app/006-story-telling/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;prachodayat.netlify.app&#x2F;006-story-telling&#x2F;2022-11-08-08-02-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are teacher, no matter which subject you teach, you should develop a habit of integrating your content in story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked movie &#x27;Inception&#x27; very much for its recursive multi layered story telling. With each layer within layer, mind opens up new avenues. It is endurance exercise for the mind like how you swim or run marathon for physical body.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have rich history of such recursive events in Maha kavya(s).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Example Bhagwad Gita - In the periphery, it is Ved Vyasa narrating Mahabharata to Ganesh ji. The outer layer is conversation between Bhagwan Ved Vyas and Janmejaya. The inner conversation is between Dhritrashtra and Sanjaya. And the core is between Krishna and Arjun. Within each layer, time slows down. Within each word, there is depth of infinity!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we were the first to invent recursive stories, powerful enough to alter brain circuits, helping curing mental diseases and keeping humans on the path of dharma!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dharma upadesa  in plain dry dull sermons and vs Dharma upadesa by recursive Maha kavya(s) and Purana(s). Makes a lot of difference in activating brain circuits and preparing it for the actions as per dharma narrated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest, Ramayana and Mahabharata recitation should be part of daily chores. It is potent therapeutic help for growing minds at home i.e. Children.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;even-reading-silently-is-not-worth-speak-up-recite-let-there-be-snvaad-let-your-brains-connect-with-each-other-and-activate-dharma-circuits-in-brain-so-that-mind-can-drive-it-for-dharmic-actions-slight-smile&quot;&gt;Even reading silently is not worth. Speak up! Recite! Let there be संवाद!! Let your brains connect with each other and activate dharma circuits in brain so that mind can drive it for dharmic actions!! 🙂&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guber argues that humans simply aren’t moved to action by &amp;quot;data dumps,&amp;quot; dense PowerPoint slides, or spreadsheets packed with figures. People are moved by emotion. The best way to emotionally connect other people to our agenda begins with &amp;quot;Once upon a time…&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;
https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fastcompany.com&#x2F;1680581&#x2F;why-storytelling-is-the-ultimate-weapon&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Can art and science go together?</title>
		<published>2022-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://prachodayat.netlify.app/002-art-science-combo/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://prachodayat.netlify.app/002-art-science-combo/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;prachodayat.netlify.app&#x2F;002-art-science-combo&#x2F;ScienceAndArt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Can art and science go together in same session?&quot; title=&quot;Can art and science go together in same session?&quot; &#x2F;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can art and science go together in same session?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All my science sessions have reference to art, culture, self. To me, it is best way to make fundamentals of science permenant on growing mind. It is the potent way to create long lasting life-science impressions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;दीपावली की छुट्टियों के बाद प्रथम दिन था और विज्ञान का वर्ग था। मेरा उद्देश्य ज्ञान तंतुओ के शरीर में फैले जाल का अनुभव करवाना था ।&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;बात प्रारंभ हुई दीपावली के अनुभवों से । प्रश्न आया रंगोली का । क्यूँ रंगोली करनी चाहिए?
बात को में खींच के ले गया रंगोली में लगने वाली ज्ञान मुद्रा पर । ज्ञान मुद्रा से गए ज्ञान तन्तुओ के तंत्र पर । ज्ञान तन्तु के तंत्र में बात की पड़ोसी ज्ञानतन्तु जालों की गतिविधि पर। फिर आए दांत और हृदय के ज्ञानतन्तुमय संपर्क पर और एक बात दृढ़ की के अच्छे आचार विचार के लिए भी दांत की अच्छी संभाल रखनी पड़ेगी।
विज्ञान के मार्ग पर दिनचर्या समझने पर कौन बालक दिनचर्या को जीवन में स्थिर करने में आलस करेगा? शिष्टाचार और शिस्त स्थिर करने हेतु योग्य मार्ग है विज्ञान का मार्ग।&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
